So I went to the refugee camp. And when I went to the refugee camp in Pakistan, there were 7.5 million refugees. 7.5 million refugees. About 90 percent of them were women and children. Most of the men have been killed or they were in war. And you know, in the refugee camp, when I went day-to-day to do a survey, I found things you never could imagine. I saw a widow with five to eight children sitting there and weeping and not knowing what to do. I saw a young woman have no way to go anywhere, no education, no entertainment, no place to even live. I saw young men that had lost their father and their home, and they are supporting the family as a 10-to-12-year old boy -- being the head of the household, trying to protect their sister and their mother and their children. So it was a very devastating situation. My heart was beating for my people, and I didn't know what to do. At that moment, we talk about momentum. At that moment, I felt, what can I do for these people? How could I help these people? I am one individual. What can I do for them? But at that moment, I knew that education changed my life. It transformed me. It gave me status. It gave me confidence. It gave me a career. It helped me to support my family, to bring my family to another country, to be safe. And I knew that at that moment that what I should give to my people is education and health, and that's what I went after. But do you think it was easy? No, because at that time, education was banned for girls, completely. And also, by Russia invading Afghanistan, people were not trusting anyone. It was very hard to come and say, "I want to do this." Who am I? Somebody who comes from the United States. Somebody who got educated here. Did they trust me? Of course not. So I really needed to build the trust in this community. How am I going to do that? I went and surveyed and looked and looked. I asked. Finally, I found one man. He was 80 years old. He was a mullah. I went to his tent in the camp, and I asked him, "I want to make you a teacher." And he looked at me, and he said, "Crazy woman, crazy woman, how do you think I can be a teacher?" And I told him, "I will make you a teacher." Finally, he accepted my offer, and once I started a class in his compound, the word spread all over. In a matter of one year, we had 25 schools set up, 15,000 children going to school, and it was amazing. (Applause) Thank you. But of course, we're doing all our work, we were giving teacher training. We were training women's rights, human rights, democracy, rule of law. We were giving all kinds of training. And one day, I tell you, one day I was in the office in Peshawar, Pakistan. All of a sudden, I saw my staff running to rooms and locking the doors and telling me, "Run away, hide!" And you know, as a leader, what do you do? You're scared. You know it's dangerous. You know your life is on the line. But as a leader, you have to hold it together. You have to hold it together and show strength. So I said, "What's going on?" And these people were pouring into my office. So I invited them to the office. They came, and there were nine of them -- nine Taliban. They were the ugliest looking men you can ever see. (Laughter) Very mean-looking people, black clothes, black turban, and they pour into my office. And I invited them to have a seat and have tea. They said no. They are not going to drink tea. And of course, with the tone of voice they were using, it was very scary, but I was really shaking up. But also I was strong, holding myself up. And, of course, by that time, you know how I dress -- I dress from head to toe in a black hijab. The only thing you could see, my eyes. They asked me, "What are you doing? Don't you know that school is banned for girls? What are you doing here?" And you know, I just looked at them, and I said, "What school? Where is the school?" (Laughter) (Applause) And they look at my face, and they said, "You are teaching girls here." I said, "This is a house of somebody. We have some students coming, and they are all learning Koran, Holy Book. And you know, Koran says that if you learn the Holy Book, the woman, they can be a good wife, and they can obey their husband." (Laughter) And I tell you one thing: that's the way you work with those people, and you know -- (Laughter) So by that time, they started speaking Pashto. They talked to each other, and they said, "Let's go, leave her alone, she's OK." And you know, this time, I offered them tea again, and they took a sip and they left. By that time, my staff poured into my office. They were scared to death. They didn't know why they didn't kill me. They didn't know why they didn't take me away. But everybody was happy to see me. Very happy, and I was happy to be alive, of course. (Laughter) Of course, I was happy to be alive. But also, as we continuously gave training during the fall of the Taliban -- of course during the Taliban there is another story. We went underground and we provided education for 80 schoolgirls, 3,000 students underground, and continuously we trained. With the fall of the Taliban, we went into the country, and we opened school after school. We opened women's learning center. We continuously opened clinics. We worked with mothers and children. We had reproductive health training. We had all kinds of training that you can imagine. I was very happy. I was delighted with the outcome of my work. And one day, with four trainers and one bodyguard, I was going up north of Kabul, and all of a sudden, again, I was stopped in the middle of the road by 19 young men. Rifles on their shoulders, they blocked the road. And I told my driver, "What's going on?" And the driver said, "I don't know." He asked them. They said, "We have nothing to do with you." They called my name. They said, "We want her." My bodyguard got out, said, "I can answer you. What do you want?" They said, "Nothing." They called my name. And by that time, the women are yelling and screaming inside the car. I am very shaken up, and I told myself, this is it. This time, we all are going to be killed. There is no doubt in my mind. But still, the moment comes, and you take strength from whatever you believe and whatever you do. It's in your heart. You believe in your worth, and you can walk on it. So I just hold myself on the side of the car. My leg was shaking, and I got outside. And I asked them, "What can I do for you?" You know what they said to me? They said, "We know who you are. We know where you are going. Every day you go up north here and there. You train women, you teach them and also you give them an opportunity to have a job. You build their skills. How about us?" (Laughter) (Applause) "And you know, how about us? What are we going to do?" I looked at them, and I said, "I don't know." (Laughter) They said, "It's OK. The only thing we can do, what we know, from the time we're born, we just hold the gun and kill. That's all we know." And you know what that means. It's a trap to me, of course. So I walk out of there. They said, "We'll let you go, go." And so I walked into the car, I sit in the car, and I told the driver, "Turn around and go back to the office." At that time, we only were supporting girls. We only had money for women to train them, to send them to school, and nothing else. By the time I came to the office, of course my trainers were gone. They ran away home. Nobody stayed there. My bodyguard was the only one there, and my voice was completely gone. I was shaken up, and I sat on my table, and I said, "What am I going to do?" How am I going to solve this problem? Because we had training going on up north already. Hundreds of women were there coming to get training. So I was sitting there, all of a sudden, at this moment, talking about momentum, we are, at that moment, one of my wonderful donors called me about a report. And she asked me, "Sakena?" And I answered her. She said, "It's not you. What's wrong with you?" I said, "Nothing." I tried to cover. No matter what I tried to do, she didn't believe me, and she asked me again. "OK, tell me what's going on?" I told her the whole story. At that time, she said, "OK, you go next time, and you will help them. You will help them." And when, two days later, I went the same route, and do you know, they were not in here, they were a little back further, the same young men, standing up there and holding the rifle and pointing to us to stop the car. So we stopped the car. I got out. I said, "OK, let's go with me." And they said, "Yes." I said, "On one condition, that whatever I say, you accept it." And they said, yes, they do. So I took them to the mosque, and to make a long story short, I told them I'd give them teachers. Today, they are the best trainers. They learn English, they learn how to be teachers, they learn computers, and they are my guides. Every area that is unknown to us in the mountain areas, they go with me. They are ahead, and we go. And they protect us. And -- (Applause) Thank you. That tells you that education transforms people. When you educate people, they are going to be different, and today all over, we need to work for gender equality. We cannot only train women but forget about the men, because the men are the real people who are giving women the hardest time. (Laughter) So we started training men because the men should know the potential of women, know how much these potential men has, and how much these women can do the same job they are doing. So we are continuously giving training to men, and I really believe strongly. I live in a country that was a beautiful country. I just want to share this with you. It was a beautiful country, beautiful, peaceful country. We were going everywhere. Women were getting education: lawyer, engineer, teacher, and we were going from house to house. We never locked our doors. But you know what happened to my country. Today, people cannot walk out of their door without security issues. But we want the same Afghanistan we had before. And I want to tell you the other side. Today, the women of Afghanistan are working very, very hard. They are earning degrees. They are training to be lawyers. They are training to be doctors, back again. They are training to be teachers, and they are running businesses. So it is so wonderful to see people like that reach their complete potential, and all of this is going to happen. I want to share this with you, because of love, because of compassion, and because of trust and honesty. If you have these few things with you, you will accomplish.
Así que me fui al campo de refugiados. Y cuando fui al campamento de refugiados en Pakistán, había 7.5 millones de refugiados. 7.5 millones de refugiados. Alrededor del 90 % eran mujeres y niños. La mayoría de los hombres habían muerto o estaban en la guerra. Y en el campo de refugiados, al estudiar día tras día la situación, encontré cosas que nunca hubiera imaginado. Vi a una viuda con de cinco a ocho niños sentada allí y llorando sin saber qué hacer. Vi a una mujer joven sin tener a dónde ir, sin educación, sin entretenimiento, ni siquiera un lugar para vivir. Vi a muchachos que habían perdido su padre y su hogar, y que apoyaban a su familia siendo niños de 10 a 12 años como cabeza de familia, tratando de proteger a su hermana y su madre y sus hijos. Así que fue una situación muy devastadora. Mi corazón latía por mi pueblo, y yo no sabía qué hacer. En ese momento, hablamos de impulso. En ese momento, sentí, ¿qué puedo hacer por estas personas? ¿Cómo podría ayudarlas? Soy un individuo. ¿Qué puedo hacer yo por ellos? Pero en ese momento, supe que la educación cambió mi vida. Me transformó. Me dio estatus. Me dio confianza. Me dio una carrera. Me ayudó a mantener a mi familia, traer a mi familia a otro país, por su seguridad. Supe en ese momento que lo que debía darle a mi gente era educación y salud, y eso es lo que hice después. Pero ¿creen que fue fácil? No, porque ahí, la educación fue prohibida para las niñas, por completo. Y también, como consecuencia de la invasión de Rusia a Afganistán, la gente no confiaba en nadie. Fue muy duro ir y decir: "Quiero hacer esto". ¿Quién soy? Alguien que viene de EE. UU. Alguien que consiguió educado aquí. ¿Ellos confiaban en mí? Por supuesto que no. Así que en realidad necesitaba construir confianza en esta comunidad. ¿Cómo voy a hacer eso? Fui y examiné y miré y miré. Pregunté. Finalmente, encontré un hombre. Tenía 80 años. Era un mullah. Fui a su tienda de campaña en el campamento, y le pregunté: "Quiero hacerle maestro". Y él me miró, y dijo: "Mujer loca, mujer loca, ¿cómo crees que puedo ser maestro?". Yo le dije: "Voy a hacerle maestro". Finalmente, aceptó mi oferta, y una vez que inicié una clase en su recinto, la voz se extendió por todas partes. En cuestión de un año, teníamos 25 escuelas establecidas, 15 000 niños yendo a la escuela, y fue increíble. (Aplausos) Gracias. Pero, claro, hacíamos todo nuestro trabajo, formábamos al profesorado. Enseñábamos derechos de las mujeres, derechos humanos, democracia, Estado de Derecho. Dábamos todo tipo de formación. Y un día, le cuento, un día estaba en la oficina en Peshawar, Pakistán. De repente, vi a mi gente llegar corriendo a las habitaciones y cerrando las puertas y me dicen, "Huye, ¡escóndete!". Y ya saben, como líder, ¿qué haces? Tienes miedo. Sabes que es peligroso. Sabes que su vida está en la línea. Pero como líder, tiene que mantenerlo unido. Hay que mantenerlo unido y mostrar fuerza. Así que dije: "¿Qué está pasando?". Y estas personas estaban invadiendo mi oficina. Así que los invité a la oficina. Entraron, y eran nueve, nueve talibanes. Eran los hombres más feos que se puedan ver. (Risas) Personas que parecían muy malas, ropa de color negro, turbante negro, y entraron en mi oficina. Les invité a tomar asiento y el té. Dijeron que no. No iban a tomar té. Y, por supuesto, por el tono de voz que estaban utilizando, estaba aterrada, estaba realmente temblando. Pero también era fuerte, aguantándome. Y, por supuesto, en ese momento, ya saben cómo me visto... Me visto de pies a cabeza en un hiyab negro. Lo único que se podía ver eran mis ojos. Me preguntaron: "¿Qué está haciendo? ¿No sabe que la escuela está prohibida para las niñas? ¿Qué está haciendo aquí?". Yo los miraba a ellos, y yo dije: "¿Qué escuela? ¿Dónde está la escuela?" (Risas) (Aplausos) Y me miran a la cara, y me dicen: "Usted está enseñando niñas aquí". Les dije: "Esta es una casa cualquiera. Tenemos algunos estudiantes que vienen, y todos están aprendiendo el Corán, el Libro Sagrado. Uds. saben, el Corán dice que si uno estudia el Libro Sagrado, la mujer, puede ser una buena esposa, y puede obedecer a su marido". (Risas) Y les digo una cosa: esa es la forma de trabajar con esas personas... (Risas) Así que en ese momento, comenzaron a hablar pashto. Hablaron entre sí, y dijeron: "Vámonos, dejémosla sola, ella está bien". Esta vez les ofrecí té de nuevo, y tomaron un sorbo y reían. En ese momento, mi personal viene a mi oficina. Estaban muertos de miedo. No sabían por qué no me mataron. No sabían por qué no me quitaban. Pero todo el mundo estaba feliz de verme. Muy feliz, y yo estaba feliz de estar viva, por supuesto. (Risas) Por supuesto, estaba feliz de estar viva. Pero también, al continuar la formación durante la caída de los talibanes... claro, durante los Talibanes era otra historia. Era bajo tierra y dábamos educación a 80 alumnas, 3 000 estudiantes bajo tierra, y continuamente los educábamos. Con la caída de los talibanes, entramos en el país, y abrimos escuela tras escuela. Abrimos un centro de aprendizaje para mujeres. Continuamente abrimos clínicas. Trabajamos con las madres y los niños. Dimos educación en salud reproductiva. Tuvimos todo tipo de educación que puedan imaginar. Estaba muy feliz. Estaba encantada con el resultado de mi trabajo. Y un día, con cuatro entrenadores y un guardaespaldas, iba al norte de Kabul, y de pronto, de nuevo, fui detenida en medio de la carretera por 19 jóvenes. Con rifles en sus hombros, bloquearon el camino. Le dije a mi chofer, "¿Qué está pasando?". Y el conductor dijo: "No sé". Les preguntó. Dijeron: "No tiene que ver con usted". Me llamaron por mi nombre. Dijeron: "Nosotros la queremos". Mi guardaespaldas salió, dijo: "Yo puedo responderles. ¿Qué quieren?". Dijeron: "Nada". Me llamaron por mi nombre. Y en ese momento, las mujeres estaban gritando y gritando dentro del coche. Estaba muy conmovida, y me dije, esto es todo. Esta vez, nos van a matar a todos. No había duda en mi mente. Pero aún así, el momento llega, y se toma fuerza de lo que creas y lo que hagas. Está en tu corazón. Crees que vale la pena, y se puede caminar sobre ello. Así que me apoyo en el lado del coche. Mi pierna estaba temblando, y salgo. Y les pregunté: "¿Qué puedo hacer por Uds.?". ¿Saben lo que me dijeron? Dijeron: "Sabemos quién es Ud. Sabemos a dónde va. Todos los días van hacia al norte, aquí y allá. Ud. entrena mujeres, les enseña y también se les da la oportunidad de tener un trabajo. Ud. construye sus habilidades. ¿Qué hay de nosotros?". (Risas) (Aplausos) "Y entonces, ¿qué hay de nosotros? ¿Qué vamos a hacer?". Los miré y le dije: "No sé". (Risas) Ellos dijeron: "Está bien. Lo único que podemos hacer, lo que sabemos, desde el momento en que nacemos, tenemos un arma y matamos. Es todo lo que sabemos". Y saben eso qué significa. Es una trampa para mí, por supuesto. Así que salgo de allí. Dicen: "La vamos a dejar ir". Y así que entré en el coche, me siento en el coche, y le digo al conductor, "De la vuelta y regrese a la oficina". En ese momento, solo apoyábamos niñas. Solo teníamos dinero para entrenar mujeres, para enviarlas a la escuela, y nada más. En el momento en que llegué a la oficina, por supuesto mis entrenadores se habían ido. Huyeron a casa. Nadie se quedó allí. Mi guardaespaldas era el único que estaba, y mi voz había desaparecido por completo. Yo estaba conmocionada, y me senté en mi mesa, y dije: "¿Qué voy a hacer? ¿Cómo voy a resolver este problema?". Porque ya entrenábamos pasando al norte. Cientos de mujeres fueron allí para capacitarse. Así que estaba sentada allí, y de repente, en ese momento, hablando de impulso, somos, en ese momento, una de mis donantes maravillosas me llamó acerca de un informe. Y ella me preguntó: "¿Sakena?" Y yo le contesté. Ella dijo: "No eres tú. ¿Qué te pasa?". Dije "Nada". Traté de ocultarle. No importaba lo que tratara de hacer, ella no me creía, y ella me preguntó de nuevo. "Está bien, dime ¿qué está pasando?". Le conté toda la historia. En ese momento dijo: "Está bien, la próxima vez, ayúdales. Ve a ayudarles". Y cuando, dos días más tarde, fui por la misma ruta, no estaban allí, estaban un poco más atrás, los mismos jóvenes, de pie allí y sosteniendo el rifle y señalándonos para detener el coche. Así que paramos el coche. Salí. Les dije: "Bueno, vengan conmigo". Y ellos dijeron: "Sí". Les dije: "Con una condición, que todo lo que digo, lo aceptan". Dijeron que sí, que lo harían. Así los llevé a la mezquita, y para hacer el cuento corto, les dije que les daría maestros. Hoy en día, son los mejores entrenadores. Aprenden inglés, aprenden a ser maestros, aprenden computadoras, y son mis guías. Cada área que es desconocido para nosotros en las zonas montañosas, van conmigo. Ellos van adelante vamos. Y ellos nos protegen. Y... (Aplausos) Gracias. Eso te dice que la educación transforma a las personas. Cuando se educa a la gente, van a ser diferentes, y hoy por todas partes, tenemos que trabajar por la igualdad de género. No solo podemos formar a las mujeres, y olvidar a los hombres, porque los hombres son los que de verdad les dan a las mujeres sus momento más difíciles. (Risas) Así que empezamos a entrenar hombres porque los hombres deben conocer el potencial de las mujeres, saber cuánto potencial tienen los hombres, y cuánto de ese mismo trabajo que están haciendo, lo pueden hacer las mujeres Así que estamos dando continuamente formación a los hombres, y realmente lo creo firmemente. Vivo en un país que era un hermoso país. Solo quiero compartir esto con Uds. Fue un hermoso país, un país hermoso, pacífico. Íbamos en todas partes. Las mujeres estaban recibiendo educación: abogadas, ingenieras, profesoras, e íbamos de casa en casa. Nunca cerrábamos nuestras puertas. Pero saben lo que le pasó a mi país. Hoy, la gente no puede salir de su casa sin problemas de seguridad. Pero queremos el mismo Afganistán que teníamos antes. Y quiero mostrarles el otro lado. Hoy en día, las mujeres de Afganistán están trabajando muy, muy duro. Están ganando grados. Están estudiando para ser abogadas. Están estudiando para ser médicas, otra vez. Están estudiando para ser maestras, y están dirigiendo empresas. Por eso es tan maravilloso ver a la gente así, alcanzar su total potencial, y todo esto va a pasar. Quiero compartir esto con Uds., por amor, debido a la compasión, y debido a la confianza y la honestidad. Si uno tiene estas pocas cosas consigo lo logrará. Tenemos un poeta, Mawlana Rumi. Dijo que teniendo compasión y amor, se puede conquistar el mundo. Y yo les digo que pudimos. Y si pudimos hacerlo en Afganistán, estoy segura al 100 % de que todo el mundo puede hacerlo en cualquier parte del mundo. Muchas, muchas gracias. (Aplausos) Gracias. Gracias.